<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>      
<!ENTITY rfc4287 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.4287.xml'>      
<!ENTITY xmlns SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.W3C.REC-xml-names-19990114.xml'>      
<!ENTITY rdfsg SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.W3C.WD-rdf-syntax-grammar-20031010.xml'>      
]>
<rfc docName="draft-hanson-oauth-mfa-latest">
  <front>
    <title>OAuth 2.0 Multi-Factor Authentication</title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Hanson" fullname="Jared Hanson">
      <organization>Auth0 Inc.</organization>
      <address>       
        <email>jaredhanson@gmail.com</email> 
        <uri>http://www.jaredhanson.net/</uri>       
      </address>
    </author>
    <date/>
    <abstract>
      <t>This specification provides a framework for the use of strong
        authentication with OAuth 2.0.  Mechanisms are specified for initiating
        an authorization session.  New authorization grant types are defined
        that allow clients to obtain access tokens within the context of a
        strongly authenticated authorization session.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Strong authentication is a method of access control that grants access
        only after multiple factors of authentication have been presented.  The
        factors typically fall into the following categories: knowledge
        (something you know), possession (something you have), and inherence
        (something you are).</t>
      
      <t>OAuth 2.0 <xref target="RFC6749"/> is an authorization framework that
        enables a third-party application to obtain limited access to a
        protected HTTP resource. In OAuth, those third-party applications are
        called clients; they access protected resources by presenting an access
        token to the HTTP resource.  Access tokens are issued to clients by an
        authorization server with the (sometimes implicit) approval of the
        resource owner. These access tokens are typically obtained by exchanging
        an authorization grant, which represents the authorization granted by
        the resource owner (or by a privileged administrator).</t>
        
      <t>This specification defines a general framework for the use of strong
        authentication within OAuth 2.0.  It provides a generic mechanism for
        indicating when strong authentication is required.  It defines
        additional extension grant types that allow strong authentication
        credentials to be presented in order to obtain access tokens.</t>
      
      <t>This use of strong authentication allows authorization servers to
        implement correspondingly strong authorization policies, including
        step-up authentication and transaction confirmation.</t>
        
      <t>Authorization servers that implement support for resource owner
        password credentials can augment existing password infrastructure by
        requiring a strong second factor prior to issuing access tokens.</t>
        
      <t>Transaction confirmation can be used to increase the level of assurance
        prior to issuing tokens for highly privileged operations, such as a bank
        withdrawl.  For example, an end-user (resource owner) can grant an
        application (client) access to her account at a brokerage firm (resource
        server).  The application is authorized to obtain real-time stock quotes
        as well as place orders, and is issued both an access token and refresh
        token.  As a matter of policy, the access token can be used to obtain
        stock quotes and is valid for 24 hours.  Every 24 hour period, the
        refresh token is used to obtain a new access token, so that access to
        stock quotes is uninterrupted.  The access token can also be used to
        place an order, but is subject to more stringent security requirements.
        Using this extension, the refresh token can be used to initiate an
        authorization transaction which, once confirmed by the user, allows
        issuance of an access token that demonstrates strong authentication and
        has a limited lifetime.</t>
        
        <section title="Notational Conventions">
          <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
            "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
            "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
        </section>
        
        <section title="Terminology">
          <t>
            This specification also defines the following terms:
            
            <list style="hanging"> 
            <t hangText="MFA Token:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
              A short-lived token representing an authorization session.</t>
            </list> 
          </t>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Protocol Flow">
      <figure title='Abstract Protocol Flow' anchor='Figure-1'>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
+----------+
| Resource |
|  Owner   |
|          |
+----------+
   v    v
   |    |
  (A)  (D)
   |    |
   v    v
+---------+                                      +---------------+
|         |>-(B)--- Authorization Grant -------->|               |
|         |                                      |               |
|         |<-(C)-------- MFA Token -------------<|               |
|         |                                      | Authorization |
|         |>-(E)-- Strong Authn Credential ----->|     Server    |
|         |             & MFA Token              |               |
|         |                                      |               |
| Client  |<-(F)------- Access Token -----------<|               |
|         |                                      +---------------+
|         |
|         |                                      +---------------+
|         |>-(G)------- Access Token ----------->|               |
|         |                                      |    Resource   |
|         |<-(H)---- Protected Resource --------<|     Server    |
|         |                                      |               |
+---------+                                      +---------------+
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        <list style='format (%C)'>
          <t>
            The client obtains authorization from the resource owner.  The
            authorization can be obtained directly from the resource owner (as
            shown), or preferably indirectly via the authorization server as an
            intermediary.  The resource owner's authorization is represented as
            an authorization grant.
          </t>
          <t>
            The client requests an access token by authenticating with the
            authorization server and presenting the authorization grant.
          </t>
          <t>
            The authorization server authenticates the client and validates the
            authorization grant, and if strong authentication is required,
            returns an error along with an MFA token.
          </t>
          <t>
            The resource owner provides the client with a strong authentication
            credential.
          </t>
          <t>
            The client requests an access token from the authorization server's
            token endpoint by including the strong authentication credential
            received from the resource owner along with the MFA token received
            during the prior access token request.  When making the request, the
            client authenticates with the authorization server.
          </t>
          <t>
            The authorization server authenticates the client and validates the
            resource owner strong authentication credential, and if valid,
            issues an access token.
          </t>
          <t>
            The client requests the protected resource from the resource server
            and authenticates by presenting the access token.
          </t>
          <t>
            The resource server validates the access token, and if valid, serves
            the request.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Authorization Session">
      <t>A client initates an authorization session by sending a token request
        to the token endpoint as described in Section 3.2 of <xref target="RFC6749"/>.</t>
      
      <section title="Token Request">
        <t>
          The client may indicate that it supports strong authentication by
          including the following parameter in the token request to the token
          endpoint.
          
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="mfa_supported"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
              OPTIONAL.  Indicates that the client support strong authentication.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        
        <figure>
          <preamble>
            The following is a non-normative example of a token request (with
            extra line breaks for display purposes only):
          </preamble>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
POST /token HTTP/1.1
Host: server.example.com
Authorization: Basic czZCaGRSa3F0MzpnWDFmQmF0M2JW
Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded

grant_type=password&username=johndoe&password=A3ddj3w&mfa_supported=1
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Token Error Response">
        <t>In addition to the error codes defined in Section 5.2 of
          <xref target="RFC6749"/>, the following error codes are specific
          multi-factor authorization flows: 

          <list style="hanging"> 
            <t hangText="mfa_required"> <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              The authorization server requires strong authentication.</t>
          </list> 
        </t>
        
        <t>In addition to the response parameters specified by OAuth 2.0, the
          following parameters MUST be included in the response when the error
          code is set to mfa_required:
        
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="mfa_token"> <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              REQUIRED.  The MFA token used to continue the authorization session.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        
        <figure>
          <preamble>
            The following is a non-normative example token error response:
          </preamble>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 403 Forbidden
Content-Type: application/json;charset=UTF-8
Cache-Control: no-store
Pragma: no-cache

{
  "error":"mfa_required",
  "mfa_token": "eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsImtpZCI6IjFlOWdkazcifQ.eyJpc3Mi
    OiJodHRwOi8vc2VydmVyLmV4YW1wbGUuY29tIiwic3ViIjoiMjQ4Mjg5NzYxMDA
    xIiwiYXVkIjpbImh0dHA6Ly9zZXJ2ZXIuZXhhbXBsZS5jb20vdG9rZW4iLCJodH
    RwOi8vc2VydmVyLmV4YW1wbGUuY29tL2F1dGhlbnRpY2F0b3JzIl0sIm1mYSI6W
    yJvdHAiLCJvb2IiXSwiZXhwIjoxMzExMjgxOTcwLCJpYXQiOjEzMTEyODA5NzB9
    .IvjKKc54lHvAOCskyEUU8Ou_-8-oXKyFS5bbq-utZPA"
}
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Obtaining Authorization using Strong Authentication">
      
      <section title="OTP Credentials Grant">
        <t>An one-time password is generated by an OTP device, which includes
          hardware devices as well as software-based OTP generators on devices
          such as mobile phones.
        </t>
        
        <section title="Access Token Request">
          <t>
            The client makes a request to the token endpoint by adding the
            following parameters using the "application/x-www-form-urlencoded"
            format per Appendix B with a character encoding of UTF-8 in the HTTP
            request entity-body:
          
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="grant_type"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
                REQUIRED.  Value MUST be set to
                "http://auth0.com/oauth/grant-type/mfa-otp".</t>

              <t hangText="otp"> <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                REQUIRED.  The one-time password.</t>

              <t hangText="mfa_token"> <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                REQUIRED.  The MFA token received when initiating the
                authorization session.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section title="Access Token Response">
          <t>If the access token request is valid and authorized, the
            authorization server issues an access token and optional refresh
            token as described in in Section 5.1 of <xref target="RFC6749"/>.
            If the request failed client authentication or is invalid, the
            authorization server returns an error response as described in
            Section 5.2 of <xref target="RFC6749"/>.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Out-of-Band Verification Code Grant">
        <t>An out-of-band verification code is obtained by challenging an out-of-band
          authenticator.
        </t>
        
        <section title="Access Token Request">
          <t>
            The client makes a request to the token endpoint by adding the
            following parameters using the "application/x-www-form-urlencoded"
            format per Appendix B with a character encoding of UTF-8 in the HTTP
            request entity-body:
          
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="grant_type"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
                REQUIRED.  Value MUST be set to
                "http://auth0.com/oauth/grant-type/mfa-oob".</t>

              <t hangText="oob_code"> <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                REQUIRED.  The out-of-band verification code.</t>

              <t hangText="mfa_token"> <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                REQUIRED.  The MFA token received when initiating the
                authorization session.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section title="Access Token Response">
          <t>If the access token request is valid and authorized, the
            authorization server issues an access token and optional refresh
            token as described in in Section 5.1 of <xref target="RFC6749"/>.
            If the request failed client authentication or is invalid, the
            authorization server returns an error response as described in
            Section 5.2 of <xref target="RFC6749"/>.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6749"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
